welcome back to the emerge podcast
today i'm joined by daniel
schmachtenberger
daniel is a social engineer and
evolutionary
philosopher and strategist he is the
founder of
critical path institute the emergence
project
and the co-founder of the neurohacker
collective
daniel has become very well known
in the weird corner of the internet
that this podcast occupies the sense
making
media the meta media whatever we're
going to call it
in any case for me personally
daniel's thinking has colored
many of the conversations i've had on
the podcast
and his formulations his kind of
abstractions
have been named by many of the people
that i have talked with
daniel is a close collaborator with
folks i've had on the show people like
jordan green hall and zack stein
daniel was also kind enough to offer to
come back
on the show if there are any follow-up
questions
uh that people have if while you're
listening to the conversation or
after you finish listening to the
conversation you have
uh some uh some questions
some curiosities that you'd like to hear
daniel reflect on
you can send them to me on twitter
i'm at d thorson or you can email them
to me
i'm at dthorsen gmail.com
i will collate those questions find a
way to kind of rank them and prioritize
them and then
maybe we'll do a sort of ama episode
with daniel
sometime in the future who knows
all right without further ado here is
daniel schmucktenberger on the emerge
podcast
[Music]
the emerge podcast is proud to be
sponsored by the monastic academy
for the preservation of life on earth
the monastic academy located in lowell
vermont
is a training center dedicated to the
amplification
of human maturity in the age of the
anthropocene
the academy trains its participants
through a unique combination
of rigorous contemplative training
project-based learning
and a disciplined commitment to ethical
behavior
all held in the context of deep
community
the monastic academy is currently
accepting applications
for the apprenticeship program this
program
lasting two or three months includes
silent retreats daily meditation
instruction
and regular authentic relating practices
this program is free other ways to
participate
include daily visits week-long retreats
or if you can work remotely joining the
academy
through the co-working program allowing
you to
deepen your practice while keeping your
job
for more information you can go to
www.monastic
academy dot com
[Music]
welcome back to emerge today on the show
i
am very excited to welcome for the first
time
daniel schmoktenberger daniel welcome to
emerge
thanks for having me daniel happy to be
here yeah
so um your thinking and i guess that
what you've shared on the internet
as you've been wrestling with our era
has already flavored many of the
conversations we've had on the show
with people like uh jordan greenhall
hansi frynakt
bonita roy you know your thinking has in
various ways
informed those conversations and so
this conversation is going to assume uh
some degree
of uh background knowledge about
your approach to the kinds of inquiries
this show is all about
collapse phase shift um human potential
yeah and and to to start off i think
i would love to hear your take on on
what i think of as the kind of current
state of play you know
my sense as an observer of culture is
that
things seem to be accelerating as they
have but there's a kind of like
i don't know some sort of point that's
been reached uh
pivot point or something you know
collapse is puncturing the mainstream
discourse you can look at the
new york times article on the rebranding
of the pinkertons to be kind of like
uh post-collapse militia uh you can look
at jem bendel's deep adaptation paper
getting just
more attention than like any other
academic paper
that gets published and it wasn't even
published it was just put on the
internet
or the fact that extinction rebellion is
gathering so much steam
and i'm curious like what are you seeing
now
and if there's anything that has changed
in your models or
expectations or sense of how the how
collapse or phase shift will unfold
yeah so you're mentioning that the
uh general zeitgeist is getting more
uh familiar with and considered about
collapse models and
i think thinking about uh the emergence
of that phenomena historically is kind
of interesting
so there have been some people talking
about
something like an eminent phase shift
that would either look like
collapse or emergence
forever right i mean for a very long
time and that's
the way i think about it is that that's
a way of thinking about the biblical
rapture story uh it's a way of being
able to interpret the
end of the mayan calendar or the end of
satyu kaliyuga in the beginning of
satyuga in the hindu system is that
the idea that we're in a time that
doesn't continue the way that this time
has been unfolding and that at a certain
point there's something like a hard fork
we can see that being a pretty old idea
right
and kind of the way i think about that
and
i'm thinking about metaphorically i
don't know what the actual history was
but let's imagine that we're thinking
about kind of the
rapture story from from christian and
you know even earlier jewish kind of
thinking so if we were
people like you and i having a
conversation like this where we're
thinking about the future
during the bronze age and
we're noticing that as we've continued
to develop
more powerful technology we have
developed more powerful technology of
warfare so
you know as soon as we get arrows and
then as soon as we get
arrows that can pierce armor and you
know
armor and all those things that there's
an escalation of military capacity on
all sides
and we can kill a lot more people from
further distances than
the records of previous warfare and it's
pretty clear that we're going to keep
developing more projectile capacity and
you know we're going to get catapults
and then cannons and whatever
and we're also developing technology for
accumulation being able to store
resources so that there's more of an
orientation to
uh accumulate surplus and the ability to
extract resources everything from you
know better saws to take trees down and
better fishing technology to
you know smithing technology and so we
can see that as our technologies
growing both our capacity to kill each
other and our capacity to unrenewably
destroy the environment and so we see
that there are deserts near our
civilization that are the results of our
unrenewable agriculture and forestry
practices
and they're growing and
that the military technology we're
getting that's up ratcheting is also up
ratcheting on the other
sides and it's not that hard to just
kind of run the scenario and say okay
if we keep increasing our technology and
using it in ways that directly harm each
other or indirectly harm the commons we
just don't get to do that forever on a
finite playing field
and so there's a reckoning that's going
to come with how we use power
as we keep getting more powerful and so
we get the kind of purgatory story that
there's
right now it's only a few patient people
profits that see that it's going to go
this way
but there's a certain point at which the
fact that we don't get to keep going
this way becomes eminently obvious to
everyone
and if we continue to try and
use our power in game theoretic ways
that advantage
self at the expense of other or commons
and in doing so we have to get more we
have to get some asymmetric power over
the other seeking to do that and
the moment we deploy the asymmetric
power it gets reverse engineered and
iterated on so all sides are
exponentially up ratcheting power that
is used to
externalize harm as soon as that becomes
eminent then there is this kind of great
reckoning of if we keep doing that
we do we don't get to keep doing that in
a sustainable way so we get something
like
a collapse in a health scenario and to
get something like a not collapse
scenario we have to be safe stewards
for our power and we don't really have
any record of the thing we call
civilization using our power all that
well right
meaning we've of course used power to do
some lovely things and a bunch of
dreadful things but if we take the
distribution of the types of choices
that we made as
sumerians or romans or british or
egyptians or whatever and we multiply
the power of how we've
made choices by an exponential set of
capacities
that self-terminates everywhere because
and this is where the mythopoetics of
heaven on earth or the consciousness
chains that would have to come
comes in which is if technology gives us
something like the power of gods we have
to have something like the love and
wisdom of gods to be able to rightly
wield it
otherwise the misapplication of that
power self-terminates
and so i think that metaphor holds quite
strongly
and i think we can kind of think of it
as that we're
entering something like the purgatory
phase where rather than a few patient
people recognizing it
you kind of have to be not paying
attention to recognize it
and whether we're looking at climate
change
or we're looking at biodiversity loss or
species extinction or specific cases
like loss of
you know pollinators or issues with
coral or
getting to you know peak oil peak
nitrogen peak resources of different
types or we're looking at
the effects of exponential terrorism or
exponential warfare or
the massive human migration issues that
could be occurring or even
accidental externalities for more
powerful tech like ai or
or crispr and biotech it's not like
there's one collapse scenario
like there's lots and lots and lots of
them and even if we protect it against
several of them all that does is move
the curve of when the collapse happens
by a tiny bit because we're developing
power on all fronts and using it in ways
where we're advantaging some metrics
meaning either advantaging some in-group
at the expense of out-groups
advantaging the near-term at the expense
of the long-term
advantaging a particular metric like gdp
at the expense of other metrics like
biodiversity
and as long as we are advantaging some
things at the expense of other things
with exponentially more capacity to do
so that's
going to be self-terminating across all
of the applications of the power and so
yeah i think it is fair to say
that we're moving into a place where at
least there is a general sensibility of
this that is increasing
and even amongst some smaller
populations like people on your
you know listenership probably some
deeper understanding that it's not one
scenario it's a lot of scenarios and
it's not the result of a few bad dumb
people
it's actually the result of the
structure of civilization itself
yeah yeah yeah and and so i'd be curious
um i i believe that you've read jem
bendel's deep adaptation paper and he
was on the show and
we explored together his sense
of what he calls the inevitable
near-term collapse
of social systems due to climate change
and obviously that's even that's just
one vector of collapse right
is is ecological related collapse and so
uh that that question of like we're past
the point of no return
and now it's sort of inevitable a lot of
people
i hear are looking at this situation
that way that we're kind of past this
point of no return
how do you relate to that possibility is
that something you're tracking
and and like do you agree with that
yeah i'm curious what your thoughts are
i think that we're past the point of no
return
uh in terms of that
the type of world order that we
have and the underlying civilization
architectures
are definitely going to collapse that
doesn't mean that the biosphere
and our species has to collapse with it
it just means that if they
are if our species is going to not
collapse with it it has to
figure out new systems for uh mediating
itself right
and um yeah so i'm
i'm not fatalistic about this i'm
looking at
which civilizations can't further which
which systems can't further from an
architectural
perspective so like let's okay there's a
bunch of things worth looking at
first we should make the distinction
between an existential risk and a
catastrophic risk meaning
if we if we describe an existential risk
as an extinction a lack of
lack to continue our the our existence
as a species
there are risks that could be fully
existential to homo sapien or even fully
existential to say all mammals or all
hydrocarbon life
but i don't think there's that many of
them that are all that probable
currently
then there are catastrophic risks where
it's like okay we're talking about
uh some humans in pockets making
it through a world war scenario or
environmental collapse scenario but we
lose
so much of what we have developed as a
civilization
and i think there are a lot more
scenarios that are more likely of that
class but for now i would just put them
all together as
um you know massive to complete collapse
type scenarios
so if we look at climate change for
instance
i don't think there are any climate
change scenarios that very reasonably
are existential
meaning directly meaning that
we create a climate where that is venus
formed where
humans just can't live in the climate i
don't think that is
likely so i do think we can have a
situation
where environmental issues that include
climate change but also include
desertification and fishery collapse and
resource issues of various kinds
lead to massive human migrations and
that those
massive human migrations lead to
uh really significantly
increased resource pressures which
definitely have a good chance
of leading to war and escalating war and
economic collapse and grid collapse and
those types of things
yeah and so uh you know in the
future thinkers podcasts it's really
important to listen to as one of the
most important podcasts i think i've
ever heard
in my estimation and in that podcast you
talk about
this idea of scaled interpersonal
coherence
as being a kind of solution to the
current problem set or problematic
architecture of our civilization
and i'm curious if there's anywhere that
you now see
signs of the emergence of this sort of
collective intelligence you know the one
that could help us thread this needle
i understand you may not be able to name
the specifics because these things are
often very fragile when they're getting
going
but even just to know that you're seeing
like embryonic versions of what you've
been calling for uh would be
yeah just curious to hear if that is
happening yet in your view
okay so when you were talking about
solutions in terms of new types of
collective intelligence and sense-making
systems that could inform new types of
choice making
new social architectures to be able to
look at what an adequate social
architecture would be
we do need to to understand adequacy we
do need to understand
the nature of the problems in current
social architecture and
you mentioned that uh a number of those
were discussed in future thinkers in
ways that took a while so
i won't take a while with it but i think
it might be worth just briefly naming
what the primary issues are
so that then we could say uh
emergent experiments that would be
interesting would be things that would
address these types of issues does that
make sense
yeah okay so briefly
we were just mentioning that there's a
lot of different types of risks that
emerge from the same underlying dynamics
i've talked about these underlying
dynamics as
generator functions which means we're
not looking at
a particular type of pollution or a
particular type of resource depletion
or a particular type of warfare we're
looking at what creates pollution
or resource depletion or warfare writ
large in the nature of how
humans coordinate activity and
if we can identify underneath all of the
future risk scenarios we can identify
you know hopefully relatively small set
of
social architectures or generator
functions that give rise to all those
problems
then we can say well rather than solve
for the instance of a particular
collapse scenario can we solve for
the class of the generator functions
writ large and
if we could find a finite set of
generator functions that we could show
to be subsumptive that all of the risks
come from these things and we could
actually solve for the class of those
generator functions
then that would be the kernel of a new
civilization model
in a civilization that would be by its
design parameters not self-terminating
and so we'll just kind of describe that
real quick
there's a lot of ways to think about why
something
why a particular system that is
autopoetic right that's self-organizing
and self-advancing why it would
self-terminate
but it's it's not uncommon if we think
about cancer in a body
cancer is a autopoetic self-terminating
thing
right so the cancer cells figure
figure that they can defect on the rest
of the body i
i am saying this in an anthropomorphic
way but they defect on
the agreement of the rest of the body in
a way that has them actually gain more
resources they consume sugar faster than
the surrounding cells and they replicate
faster so they're doing an increased
consumption and reproduction
but in doing so they're actually
debasing the integrity of the entire
system
and if they succeed if the rest the
system doesn't reverse them
you know stop them doing that then you
actually have the most cancer cells
right before the body dies
and then they all die and so as they
are in the short term advancing what it
seems like is their mission they are
also debasing the substrate upon which
they depend
and because the cancer cells emerge out
of a healthy body that can
live for a lot longer than a cancerous
body can
and so in general we can say that if you
have any system that emerges
out of a base a base layer a more
fundamental layer
if that emergent layer debases the layer
that it emerges out of and depends upon
that system is going to self-terminate
eventually right you can't debase your
own substrate sustainably
but we can see that nature gives rise to
humans we see that humans give rise to
technology
and then humans use the tech to
uh kill each other debase nature
and make better tech to do both of those
things
that's an unstable scenario and so
if we want to have stability of
creatures that have the amount of power
that technology enables us to have that
is totally unprecedented in the rest of
life
then if nature gives rise to humans and
humans give rise to tech the tech has to
be in service to the actual resilience
of nature so that there is a closed
resiliency loop well building
technology and infrastructure with
the goal of increasing the orderly
complexity and the meta-stability and
anti-fragility of nature itself is not
something we've really
like ever done but it's something we
obviously have to do
right and so we can start thinking about
what would what currently is
underneath how we develop tech there's
both a set of motivation structures
economic structures
um and a type of sense making we develop
a particular piece of technology for a
particular goal
but it's going to interact with a lot of
things other than the goal for which we
made it which are areas where that can
create
externality of harm right so there's
both a change of
the motivation of how we do technology
the comprehensivity of it
the nature of the sense making process
that would have to change for us to be
able to do tech properly
so um
thinking about a civilization that is
debasing its own substrate
self-terminating just so people kind of
get a sense
um of why self-termination you know
would happen in that way
a simple way of thinking about the
generator functions that
a generator function that i think is
familiar to most people is just a topic
of perverse incentive
writ large the the idea of what perverse
incentive is
which is if we want to look at
biodiversity loss and we say okay why
are we extincting so many species
and why are the large fish species so
overfished and the whales and
why have we cut down so many of the
trees as soon as we have a system where
the trees are worth more debt as lumber
than they are alive
or the fish are worth more dead than
they are swimming in the ocean
and war raises gdp and is more
profitable than peace and sick people
are more profitable than healthy people
then and on and on underneath all of
those problems is a perverse incentive
complex where someone has a lot more
incentive to cause
a problem than they do to not cause a
problem right
yeah and if we take a look at the like
dead trees example
we get this multipolar trap where
i don't me cutting down this tree or
these few trees is not killing all
forests
but it is getting my family meaningfully
ahead and my f
you know like if i leave them my family
doesn't get ahead and doesn't even
eat right and if i do this then my
family gets ahead
and so i don't
think about it at kind of a great
debasing our whole substrate scale and i
don't even think i have
options because i don't necessarily know
another way other than cutting the trees
down and if i don't cut the trees down
someone else is going to cut the trees
down so i don't even have an option to
leave them
and so if someone else going to cut them
down anyways then i might as well do it
to be able to get my family to move
forward so we have a situation in which
each
person or each company or each country
acting in its own
rational near-term self-interest leads
and so each person doing what actually
seems smart to them in the near term
is actually suicidal for the whole over
the long term it's a dysfunctional
collective intelligence where the
coupling of
the choices of the individual actors
doesn't couple to good choices at the
level of the whole system
right so we have a system where
for the most part nobody really wants
climate change
there are some examples there are some
exceptions that matter
like you know if i was russia i would be
pretty stoked on climate change because
the opening up of the northern passage
would be economically powerful
but for the most part nobody wants
climate change
and yet all of us are doing actions that
are advancing climate change
and but in our own self-interest i need
to just put some gas on the car to drive
and what i'm doing is so tiny relative
to the whole thing and on and on whether
it's an individual actor
corporate actor military actor and in
the presence of what everybody else is
doing and so there's this weird thing
where the invisible hand of the market
the emergent property of everybody
interacting where they're all doing
utility maximization
within a current system is perpetuating
the system
so the invisible hand of the market is
driving climate change and driving
biodiversity loss and up ratcheting
exponential warfare even though no
actual actors really want any of those
things
and that is a dysfunctional collective
intelligence right
but basically a scenario where we have
game theoretic actors whether it's an
individual person or a family or a tribe
or a nation-state or a corporation or a
political party or a race
that identifies as an in-group in
competition
for scarce resources with some other out
group
if they're acting in their own interest
then
and they're empowered by the ability to
create technology
whether we're talking about social
technology like
democracy or markets or physical
extraction capacity from the environment
or information tech or warfare tech
the difference between humans and all
the rest of animals and nature
in this way because obviously in nature
there's a lot of cooperation there's a
lot of symbiosis but there's also
competition
and there are rivalries dynamics and we
might see
two animals of the same species actually
competing over reproductive opportunity
in a rivalrous way and even in a
zero-sum way and we might see a predator
and prey in a zero-sum dynamic
one specific predator hunting one prey
animal
and yet we still see this kind of meta
stability in nature
and so we take this idea that
you know hey the lions chasing the
gazelle
eat the slow gazelle they don't catch
the fast ones so then
the fastest of the gazelles are the ones
that reproduce and the gazelles get
faster as a result of what the lions are
doing so hey this rivalry is actually
good the competition drives innovation
the lions as a whole if they weren't
there
the gazelles would actually overpopulate
themselves into extinction so the
gazelles need the lions and
the lions make the gazelles better and
the speed of the gazelles
getting away a lot of the time has the
slow lion starve so the fast lions get
faster
and you know etc and so we see that this
rivalry in this competition
is actually necessary because they
couldn't maintain without it
and it upratchets everybody's capacity
and drives this thing called evolution
and so we're like okay well that's how
nature works so we should work that way
and hey that's how theory of markets
works right
and this is basically a simple way of
understanding social darwinism where we
reify
theory of markets as if it's a darwinian
process
and we say evolution is defined by
an environmental niche and then
selection dynamics inside of that niche
and the selection dynamics
are a result of three things mutation
survival selection and mate selection so
the mutation
happens randomly in evolution right it's
not consciously controlled where a lion
gets to say
i want my dna to mutate in this way it's
just mutation
occurs from from gamma rays from
oxidative stress from copying errors
from whatever
and so some mutations lead to a slightly
longer neck
and if that is advantageous because
there are leaves up high that aren't
being eaten
and a couple that have a similar
mutation breed together that moves in a
direction towards giraffes right
and but most mutations won't be
advantageous and most of them will fail
so we have basically mutation and then
which mutations survive
most of them aren't going to survive
they're not even going to be able to eat
which and then of the ones that survive
they mate with each other
and uh only those
genetics only those offspring go through
so for something to be selected for long
term
it has to survive and it has to be able
to reproduce so
we think about markets and we say well
demand in a supply and demand dynamic
demand is like an environmental niche
there is some resource there and
something is going to emerge to fill
that niche to create a source of supply
so then it's usually not one something
it's a number of some things competing
and so you get multiple people or
companies trying to make a product or
service to fulfill that demand but they
do slightly different versions they have
their own innovations and that's like
mutation
right it's like modifications on the
product
and so most the companies are going to
fail and
only the company that actually figures
out how to provide the best value at the
best price is the one that's going to
make it through
i.e survival selection and then maybe
you got a couple companies that are
doing something
really positive and if they were to
join ip it'd be even better so you get a
merger or an acquisition
and that's like kind of mate dynamics
where you get recombinatorial dynamics
on the
underlying innovations and so we say
well great so
markets drive innovation and
uh as a result of they drive innovation
and the competition pressure is actually
a healthy good thing and that's how we
get new tech and that's how we actually
get higher quality of life for everybody
this is of course not true at all and
silly even though like
it's not not true at all there's some
truth to it but the reason that
it is fundamentally not true and we
can't model ourselves in a darwinian way
is because the other animals can't
upratchet their rival risk capacity with
technology
and that really changes everything and
so if we look at an apex predator say we
take an orca or a lion or a polar bear
one lion just can't do that much harm to
all
lions or to all gazelles or to its whole
ecosystem it's just not that powerful
but one person today
with nuclear weapons or biotech can
really a lot of stuff up
and so the system becomes very fragile
when one person or one group has so much
power relative to the entire system
right our technology has allowed us to
upratch it our power
relative to each other and relative to
the other species and relative to the
system as a whole
in a way that nothing in evolution has
anything even closely resembling
and so you think about a great white and
its ability to uh
catch fish and then you think about an
ocean trawler with a mile long drift net
in its ability to catch
fish and you're like oh we are clearly
not apex predators we can't model
ourselves as apex predators anymore
because
if we keep competing for who's apex
predator in that way but we can pull up
miles of fish at once we clearly debase
the whole the planet's ability to
support us
and so the key thing to really get is
that
in nature the mutations that lead to
advantage
are symmetrically distributed across the
entire ecosystem
so all lions are undergoing mutation and
all gazelles are and there's similarity
from some lions to others and there's
similarity in the mutation
dynamics between the lions and the
gazelles and also the
everything else so you never get the
lions getting a thousand times more
powerful in one
step irrespective of the gazelles having
a similar step
if they did you would actually lose the
meta-stability of the whole system
the lion's gonna get a tiny bit faster
or the gazelle will get a tiny bit
faster
through a mutation as that happens
then the slowest of the gazelles will
get eaten the faster ones will now
rebreed and combine and so you get this
thing where
power increases anywhere lead to power
increases everywhere because there's a
symmetry in the distribution of power
so that's a result of the symmetrical
distribution of mutation pressures and
the co-selective pressures
the fact that as one is elevating it is
having real-time interaction with the
other one
so they're also elevating which is why
an invasive species can ruin a whole
ecosystem
is that it didn't have co-selective
pressure so if we bring an invasive
species in that figured out
how to have some kind of power that the
whole ecosystem is not adapted to deal
with
it can really massively up a system
well
us developing the kind of tech that we
have makes us like
like a super invasive species across
every ecosystem
with nothing ever being able to really
check that capacity
and so this is where when we recognize
no other animal has the ability to
destroy whole ecosystems or build
new types of ecosystems or genetically
engineer new species and hybridize new
species and extinct species so
we we don't have power like apex
predators where we can model ourselves
that way and all do our own competitive
dynamics we have
power to affect the world that really
only nature had
previously and nature is tending to the
orderly complexity of the whole
so if we have that much power it has to
be used to actually tend to the orderly
complexity and the metastability of the
whole
or bust right and this very much goes
back to this
kind of earlier narrative of made in the
image and likeness of
god and having god-like powers emerge we
have to have some god-like wisdom
and love for how to steward that or we
get
um destruction so coming to that and
coming back
to the generator function topic to then
be able to answer a question of
what needs to emerge and where do we see
it happening
so three generator functions that relate
to perverse incentive and re
relate to debase our substrate and these
things but i'll say
more specifically so that we can look at
what needs to emerge as something that
can deal with these things
one is we can't keep running rivalrous
dynamics
with exponentially more power and
so rivalrous dynamics can work fine in
nature
but as soon as we get techne we get the
capacity to
create massive jumps in power where we
can increase our predative capacity
faster than the environment can
increase its resilience to our predative
capacity we can't keep running it that
way
so given that exponential tech is
happening and it can't really be
stopped then we have to develop
anti-rivalrous systems for the
development and deployment of that
tech and anti-rival risk means
a nation-state that has its own metrics
right like its own balance sheet of its
resources its gdp
its security its longevity its health
care metrics
a nation state that can benefit its
people
independently of and even at the expense
of other nations or the commons
is a basis for a rivalrous game and a
corporation that can benefit its
shareholders at the expense of other
shareholders of the market writ large or
the environment
or all the way down to individual
private balance sheets and
private property type dynamics are all
the basis of rivalrous games so of
course
they have been very useful for the kinds
of progress we have made thus far
they've been so useful that if i say
something like problems associated with
private property people freak out in the
way that like fundamentalist religious
people freak out when i'm talking
saying that their religion isn't the
only truth they freak out because they
assume that what i want is
is stalin's idea to be instantiated
right
um and that we want some dreadful thing
called marxism that was already figured
out to be not true and look
so
it's important that we recognize
that if we don't understand the nature
of the problem well we can't solve it
if we do understand the nature of the
problem well we might be able to come up
with solutions that we've never
tried before of course we're not going
to suggest previous systems that also
sucked we're going to suggest systems
that we haven't done
yet that involve new insights and new
capacities but we've got to even define
the problem well to know what we're
trying to solve
this relates to another generator
function that i'll
get to i guess i'll get to it now so the
first one is we've got to figure out
anti-rivalrous dynamics so that
we're not see one something else to
understand about the rivalry is it's not
just
us going to physical warfare with each
other or competing for economic
extraction from the planet or figuring
that to increase on profit margins we
externalize more of our costs to the
commons in the form of pollution
it's also that in a rival risk game
true information about reality is a
source of strategic competitive
advantage
if i know where the gold is or where the
water is or whatever as a tribe then and
but there's not enough for the other
tribe then i want to hoard that
information from ourselves
and because i don't want the other tribe
to stumble upon it i even want to
disinform them about where it is right
and so you'll notice that in
any competitive game any rivalries
zero-sum type game
disinformation emerges not just
withholding but actually disinforming
it's what a bluff is in poker
or it's what faking left and going right
is in soccer or football right like
we see it everywhere and of course we
see it in the history of tribal
warfare all the way on to you know
advanced civilization type dynamics
but the problem is in rivalrous games
multiplied by a world with exponential
information technology
we get exponential disinformation
capacity
and meaning that we can have a facebook
feed that says
that ends up having an ai algorithm that
optimizes it
for stickiness for you which means
whatever hijacks your limbic system the
most which means
whatever version of information ends up
appealing to your in-group dynamics and
your biases and your
fear and susceptibility and like that
and
totally independent of actual good
information
and so if we think about the world today
from the point of view of
the damage not just to the physical
commons but to the epistemic commons
because there's incentive to
have disinformation well how the
can we solve any problems if we don't
even know what the problems are
because the epistemic commons is so
destroyed that nobody has sense making
how do you do good choice making without
sense making well you don't right
and so if we ask well how long do we
have
before the coral die off what will the
effect of the coral dying off be
will they all die off or will thermally
resistant species emerge are they dying
off
mostly from temperature or from ph
change from carbonic acid or from
nitrogen affluent affecting the
phosphorus cycle or from trophic
cascades from
a lot of the large fish and whale
species so
how do we deal with that thing why was
nuclear why was north korea about to be
a nuclear war with us a year ago and now
everything is fine for the first time
since the 70s what the happened
did they really have technical nuclear
capabilities how much stuff really
leaked out of fukushima is fukushima
solved now
what is the real risk with ai elon says
it's too late bill gates says there's no
risk at all
what we find is that on the most
concerning issues in the
world that are the
most pertinent to the continuation of
life on earth
everybody gives up on sense-making or
defects to believing what their in-group
believes because it's too hard
to actually figure stuff out
and when i say defect i mean defects on
their own sense making
and so rival risk dynamics are going to
lead to not only
physical warfare and economic warfare
but also information and narrative
warfare which
the pollution of the epistemic commons
through that
ends up being a destruction of
sense-making and the capacity to even
know what a good choice would be
to even know what issues we're trying to
make choices in service to
and so of course if we have x if we have
more people with more
power per capita you know totally that
is increasingly blind
moving increasingly powerfully and
quickly that's not a good scenario
and so here's something i've mentioned
with regard to this one and
and sense making is
so many people have tried to figure out
the vaccine thing right like wait are
vaccines
totally safe or are they totally bad or
is it like maybe
the ones that cure polio are worth it
but not the flu ones or maybe
the problem was to marisol but without
the themarisol they're
fine or maybe or they try to figure out
the
was lyme disease a bio weapon or they
tried to figure out what really happened
with 911 or whatever it is or
the current state of ai and they get
so much conflicting information that
they just give up
yeah right and they give up on actually
making sense of it
but then what happens you have to say
well what does it mean to give
up on making sense of the world you live
in in the most consequential topics
well it's a form of nihilism right
this it's a kind of epistemic nihilism
because if reality is meaningful
then i need to understand it to know how
to interact in an appropriate way
and if i give up on understanding it
because it seems impossible or too
hard
can i actually make choices
that are aligned with what's meaningful
if i have no idea of what world i live
in
and so you know something i can talk
about what is emerging or not or what
i would encourage is for people to look
at the nature of their epistemic drive
and their epistemic nihilism and like
how much
are they actually committed to making
sense earnestly of the world they live
in as a basis
to have their choice possibly be
meaningful
come back to that because i want to
finish these general functions and i've
talked for a long time and you probably
have questions so
briefly we'll say rivalrous dynamics we
gotta
address the other thing is intrinsic to
how we do problem solving
is that for the most part humanity
solves problems in ways that make worse
problems
there's not that many exceptions and
whether we're creating a
piece of technology to solve a problem
or we're creating a bill
you know or political solution or we're
creating a new set of
mimetics for like a social solution
or whatever any of the methods we have a
new company for a market solution
so you look at it and you say all right
well
it was we were running out of easy big
game
and so there was a problem of feeding
enough people and whatever so we figured
out the plow
well the plow was the awesome for us but
it was also the beginning of massive
desertification
and having enough surplus that war was
really advantageous for other people to
come capture our surplus
and the beginning of the types of animal
husbandry that led to
so many of the problems in the world and
actually the beginning of certain types
of
fundamental patriarchies and we're like
wow a lot of things got up by the
nature of how we did the plow thing
and if we all the way back to stone
tools if we hadn't got stone tools
there'd be no environmental issues
right like we wouldn't have went and
became the apex predator in every
environment and started extincting
earlier species
if we hadn't got the wheel we come to
modern time we say all right we
we have you know i think this example is
funny but it's actually a
a good one the internal combustion
engine to be able to make the automobile
was super helpful for us we could travel
further faster easier than we could by
horse
and carriage by a lot and we were trying
to solve the problem of the limitation
of horses that we had to feed them
that they all over the place you
know those types of things
and so we the internal combustion engine
solved
the horseshit problem right london was
covered in horseshit
and the other associated horse
difficulties and that's awesome and we
all like the quality of life associated
with cars
but then we look at the proliferation of
internal combustion engines
that left cars and also went into you
know
tanks and trucks and ships and whatever
and we recognize that all of the oil
spills
in the amazon and the valdez and the you
know
gulf and whatever and all the wars over
oil and the destabilization of the
middle east forever and
all of the global economy based on the
us petrodollar
and climate change itself and all of
those issues are the result of the
success of solving the horseshit problem
and because what happens is
for us to solve a problem we define the
problem in a narrow way
right the the narrow problem is defined
in
one or two or five metrics so we want
the carriages to be able to go faster
with out the limitation of horses or
something right
and so we're working on a solution to
that narrowly defined problem but the
solution we create is going to interact
with the complexity of the actual world
in a lot of metrics that weren't part of
what we were designing to optimize
and so we didn't say also in as
environmentally sustainable way that
doesn't
create oil spills and wars over oil and
you know we weren't factoring those
things
but for the solution to really be a
solution to a problem it has to be
larger than the problem it has to be
able to overtake the problem and if it
does overtake the problem
and it solves certain definitions of the
problem narrow definitions but that it
interacts with the complex world
where it ends up externalizing harm in
other areas but it's larger than the
original problem was those places where
it externalizes harm will probably be
larger
or more complex and you know another way
of saying it is just
as humans develop more power we are just
shitty users of power currently right
um so that's coming back to the
rivalrous thing but it's also coming
back to the even not rival risk just we
aren't sense making well enough to say
if we're making a new piece of tech are
we making something
that even if we weren't doing it for a
rivalrous purpose isn't going to
externalize harm because we're being
adequately considerate of
not just defining the problem in a
narrow way but defining the problem
embedding space
where we can make sure that our solution
doesn't cause worse problems
and so this this is a fundamental change
in
not the nature of whether we're trying
to serve a
rival risk goal but the nature of our
sense making to understand complexity
better
and to be able to understand the
embedding space of our solutions better
so this is another thing at the
generator function that we have to
address is we have to
define problems in such a way that the
solution to that problem
is actually omnipositive rather than
positive for something and damaging for
something else
because it's not just rival risk groups
it's also rivalrous metrics
right a metric based on theory of
trade-offs where we benefit something
and harm a bunch of other things and
maybe things that we hadn't even
anticipated
is going to create inexorable problems
especially as we're as powerful as we
are
so there's one other generator function
i can get into but i feel like i've
talked for a long time so
maybe i'll take a break now and see if
framing things up this way
uh if you have any questions on it or
thoughts before we start to say
well what is emerging that's actually
interesting
yeah well let's let's wrap up the
generator function
like list let's let's finish it and then
i i want to
respond and we can explore what's going
to emerge i think that will work well
so the last one briefly is that
the way we have made technology
is fundament fundamentally problematic
in and you'll notice all three of these
relate but
there are distinctions it's
fundamentally problematic independent of
how we use it
there's this idea that tech is not good
or bad its value is neutral and it's
whether we use
whether we use it in service of which
values we can use a hammer to build a
house or to
you know hit somebody as a weapon this
is not true
technology has in certain fundamental
and inexorable effects
in its existence that we actually have
to factor
and
so inherent to increasing
power is you know
the nature of how embedded within a
rivalrous game theoretic dynamic it will
lead to the utilization of that power
for rivalrous purposes you can't
not use it for rivalrous purposes inside
of those dynamics
so that's how it relates to the the
first topic that's the multipolar trap
and where if if anyone uses it for the
up purpose everybody has to or
they lose by default
and we can't assume that other people
aren't going to so we want first mover
advantage on using it for the up
purpose
right and but then als
also so technology embedded within a
rivalrous context will get used for
adverse purposes
technology defined in narrow ways ends
up causing these problems
the other one but as we even look at
things like
the biosphere
is made up mostly of six atoms
that almost all organic life is made out
of and trace amounts
of the rest of the periodic table but
most of the nickel and the chromium and
the iron and the uranium and the lead
and the
mercury is bound in rocks way deep
underground far away from the biosphere
and it actually took geological
processes and hydrological and then
early biological process
billions of years to get it that way
right to get the distribution of stuff
where we mostly had the organic elements
all circling within a very narrow
biosphere so the
tree is made of the same stuff that the
frog and the gazelle and the
lion and the virus are all made out of
right
and as a result of that when the tree
dies or the lion dies the microbes can
eat it and
then the tree can eat it and the and so
the actual
elements of which everything is made are
the same elements with similar
distribution and so we can have closed
cycle process on it
now as soon as we start mining and we
start pulling up things that are
fundamentally toxic to biology right
the lead the mercury the arsenic the
whatever are all
toxic things we start pulling it up in
huge amounts and then we start doing the
smelting and refining where we have both
the active product is toxic and the
tailings are also toxic and now we're
leaving them up here in the biosphere
we're undoing what took billions of
years to make which was the right
elemental constituents for a healthy
biosphere
well that's a fundamental problem right
like so
either we have to make our built world
mostly out of the same elements that
nature make stuff out of
or if we're going to use other elements
we have to figure out how to have
closed-loop atomic cycling on them so we
don't have to keep taking them out of
nature and where they don't become
pollution they become like atomically
accounted for
cycled processes and where those
processes that we create we can ensure
aren't going to break down into the
future
so inherent to the nature of something
like mining
is a inherent toxicity independent of
how we think we're going to use the
stuff
right we can give a bunch of other
examples of like inherent to the nature
of an internal combustion engine is it
can't not pollute and it can't not
depend on resource extraction
it's built into the nature of the tech
it doesn't have anything to do with what
we try to use it for
and this has something to do with
making things that are totally different
than the evolutionary
precedent of the biosphere and of a
different kind we make complicated
systems
nature's complex systems also the
interface between the complicated and
complex is that
the complex is anti-fragile you burn a
forest it regrows
the complicated stuff that we build is
fragile you burn a house down it doesn't
regrow
and so as we are killing more and more
of the anti-fragility of nature
and converting it into the
complicatedness of the human-built world
we're decreasing the anti-fragility of
the biosphere and making an increasingly
fragile human-built sphere that's also a
collapse scenario
so this doesn't mean we aren't going to
have tech but it means we have to think
about it fundamentally differently we
have to think about it in a much more
considerate holistic way where we're
thinking about what is intrinsically the
entire effect across the entire
supply chain of effect of the
development of this tech
not just the really obvious effect of
how i utilize it
and so again this requires a different
level of both motive
and sense-making capacity to be able to
develop it rightly
so now when we look at all of the
catastrophic
possible risks whether we're looking at
any of the environmental dynamics or
social collapse or warfare or
unintended consequence of exponential
tech we can see
these generator functions underneath and
driving
all of those scenarios so then we can
say
if we could solve for these generator
functions categorically
which means methods for humans
interacting
that is anti-rivalrous that is building
tech in relationship with the natural
world in a meta-stable
way and that is defining
problems in a comprehensive enough way
that the solutions don't create worse
problems
then we would actually have a human
organizational system a choice-making
system that was not
driving its own collapse
[Music]
great so thank thank you daniel
i'm having uh the a similar experience
that i often have
when i listen to you speak where
there's a way in which i feel like i i
get what you're saying like on both an
intuitive and a conceptual level like as
you're saying it i feel like you're
pulling me into your world
but then like the typically you know i'm
not i'm not participating in the
conversation the conversation is on a
podcast or something that i'm listening
to
the conversation then ends and i feel
like
oh i like understand the problem
real well now
and i see like how big and how
deep it is for the first time
again you know every time i hear it
listen to you speak it's like it on
boards this
way of seeing again and it's just it
like i don't
i almost don't know what to do with that
and there's actually a sense of
in me often of like helplessness because
now i see the problem and how big it is
how vast it is and how like
deeply it's encoded into the structure
of both the
the system that i live in like my
civilization and even my own
consciousness
but then like the work of just even
reformatting my own
consciousness is like real real hard and
then i think oh and we have to do this
for a lot of people and then we also
have to do it for
all the systems up and down the stack
and i'm like
whoa that's a like i i guess
what what comes from that is you know i
feel like you're in a kind of unique
position and i almost just want to ask
you like
before we get into what you're seeing
that's emerging it's like
are you are you optimistic that we're
gonna be able to like
do this
yeah so most of us have a kind of
learned helplessness right
where we really want to help the
homeless person that we're walking
past we really actually don't feel good
about our busyness
to get to something that doesn't matter
that much having us walk past another
human that's actually really hurting
and yet there's so many homeless people
and we could spend our whole life
doing it that way and not really touch
it and that's just one tiny issue and
there's a learned helplessness where
i don't feel like i can keep caring
in the same way if i can't act on the
care it's too devastating
and so i start putting blinders on and i
start numbing
in a particular way because i can only
care about stuff i can do stuff about
and it seems like i can do so
so both my impossibility to respond
and my impossibility to even make sense
of adequately well our my impossibility
to respond will have me turn sense
making off
also my and care off my inability to
even make
sense of things will have me turn care
off and so
i'll tell you a little bit about kind of
my process
i'm i'm sharing some things that
i've come to understand or how i see
things as a result of
you know somewhat long curve of really
trying to make sense of what the
problems are in the world
but i started with much smaller
definition of the problems right it was
like it started for me that the problem
was factory farms
and then it expanded to know we actually
do up stuff to lots of animals
and then like and it kept expanding in
steps as i would work with it but at
each step there was a devastation
of both how horrific and how huge the
problem was
and then based on that sense making and
the care and then there was an
up leveling of okay well what could i do
to help this and a kind of agency that
would emerge
but then as i would work with the
solution that emerged i would realize it
wasn't a real solution because the
problem was actually deeper and bigger
than i was thinking it was now solving
the wrong problem
so okay we're going to work and put the
fences around the elephant preserve so
the poachers can't get to them to
protect the elephants
but given that even when we so we
succeed at that but we haven't addressed
the poverty of the poachers
who can't feed their kids any other way
and we haven't addressed a macro economy
that creates poverty
because of a power law distribution on
wealth and we haven't created
affected the mindset towards animals and
we haven't affected population dynamics
and all those things and so
as a result when we succeed at
protecting the elephants because the
fences go up
the poachers move to start hunting the
white rhino that's more endangered than
the mountain gorilla right this was an
actual experience i had when i was 13
working with
activism project and i'm like wow
the best solution because it didn't
understand the problem well enough
actually made a worse problem it moved
the harm to a more sensitive area
so then understand the larger definition
of the problem and then
try to work on a solution there and that
would happen again and so then that took
me on a process to
kind of the maximum abstraction of
generator functions of all the things
right
but at each step as there was a deeper
understanding of the nature of the
problems there was a while before there
was a
up leveling of a sense of agency now if
i'm going straight to the most
abstract in general case there aren't
all those steps of the up leveling of
agency and then there's going to be like
oh
i went from thinking about what i
could do with a community garden
to you know how do we
deal with the nature of how human sense
make technology differently and
rivalrous dynamics writ large globally
and so something i can say
is like so part of my process this may
or may not be relevant for anybody but
part of my process was
in facing the actual situation of the
world
was there were a few vows that i made
when i was pretty young actually
teenager the first vowel was
that i would never turn away from the
pain of the world
like like decide i'm not gonna um
go to the factory farm and i have an
opportunity or
avoid the poor area or turn off the peta
video that i wanted to actually see
the world that i lived in and what was
going on
because i didn't want to be able to
be live in a blind bubble right
so that was the first vowel and then the
second vowel of course when you start to
do that you're
it's devastating and so then the
next vowel was
to feel all of it and not go numb
and then the next vowel was to knock if
if not going numb
not getting stuck in anger and blame
and then the next vow is to also not get
stuck in hopelessness or overwhelm
those were all basically unacceptable
choices
so the first one of i just won't look at
the problems i will live in a tiny
bubble where i get to feel like i'm
succeeding while there's massive
suffering and torture happening is a
kind of dissociation that makes me as if
a sociopath right i'm stoked
there's huge pain in the world but i
don't have to care about it
so i'm like all right that doesn't work
and
going numb getting stuck in blame or
getting overwhelmed doesn't work so it's
like the only
way through is to say i'm gonna
feel it all i'm gonna recognize
that the devastation the anger whatever
is a result of love which is
if i didn't love the animals if i didn't
love the kids if i didn't love the
environment if it wasn't beautiful to me
i wouldn't care that it was being harmed
but underneath
every one of underneath the fear the
anger everything
is a reality that is so beautiful that i
love which is why i care
so then i trace it back to the love and
i feel that
and i also tune in not just to the
tragedies that are happening and could
happen but also to the intrinsic beauty
and meaningfulness of life
and then i say okay i have some agency i
don't have
god's you know omnipotence but i have
some agency
so what do i do with that agency
in service of what i care about and
you know every time i
meet a nurse who's who actually really
cares
about the people that she's nursing and
makes the pain of what they're
experiencing when they go to the
hospital less painful has them feel
cared about
like i feel this i feel this
kind of existential relief that she's
doing that
or he's doing that and every time i find
someone who is
tending to street dogs and tijuana
or anything even if it's not addressing
the generator functions of x-risk like
all those things matter
and for a lot of people they will
understand the big picture
and they'll say i'm glad some people are
working on it i care about all of it but
based on the sense making i currently
have
and based on what i know how to do this
is where i can actually add
value and the last thing i would want to
do
is have is have the nature of my
communication
say because those actions aren't totally
sufficient for everything
that you would feel less motivated to
take them no i want people to feel
deeply motivated to do the things that
they actually can do
that are expressions of their care
[Music]
and some people will be oriented to the
kind of abstractions
to say well how would we build a new
resource provisioning system a new
economics that reverse
that removes perverse incentive um or a
new collective intelligence system that
doesn't have some of the failings of our
existing governance systems
and so the people who are called to
abstractions
and to systems like that awesome
i want you to work on those things but
whatever it is that you're called to
there's a lot of things that actually
need to happen
and just because something doesn't meet
the sufficiency doesn't mean it's not
necessary
right there's a lot that's necessary
and so you know these vows for me
i'm sharing because they're ones that i
hope other people take
a version of their own version of which
is
how do i stay connected to what i care
about in the world and how do i
stay empowered in my relationship to
what i care about
thank you for that that feels really
important uh
to to to presence after uh
the work you did to to name the
generator functions
and yeah so now that we have that
ground covered conceptually uh what are
you seeing
that is emerging that is sufficient
perhaps to base a new civilizational
operating system on or however you want
to frame it yeah what are you seeing
that's emerging
it's a very interesting question
um
in terms of things that are seeable
uh there's nothing that maps to
sufficiency yet
that doesn't mean there isn't progress
um
so do we see types of collective
intelligence processes
that could solve problems without making
worse problems and types of resource
provisioning that could solve rivalrous
dynamics at scale
no not yet do we at least see more
people
understanding some of these dynamics and
taking them seriously in a way they
hadn't
yes that's one thing that's emerging is
actually just
even a higher level of conversation and
consideration which is always going to
precede
the ability to address the things
emerging in that conversation
now you know if we look at things like
uh dow stack or back feed
that's working on kind of dao based
governance structures
or um you know holochain or other
of the groups that are kind of at the
front end of the decentralized computing
decentralized governance
process that are working on better
systems of governance and collective
intelligence
do they map to sufficient yet no
are they making progress that is
actually meaningful over
previous systems yes
um so that's an example
of some spaces that are interesting as
we see
more groups starting to explore
um things like collective intelligence
and small group process
and seeing how shared sense making can
work
better than just the org chart of a
corporation or a government or a
traditional academic type dynamic
i think the collective intelligence
group process space
there are things that are moving in the
right direction
it's interesting on the topic of things
like the work in
psychology or psychospiritual
development
feels like it is both some of the most
important and most problematic work
happening
um because
the software of rivalry is embedded in
us right it's embedded in our psyche
and so as
long as i've got underlying insecurities
that i've been trained have to be
resolved by getting other people's
approval of me in relationship to being
better on finite metrics than the other
guy
then we're just we just can't work with
those types of people to make
effective collective intelligence very
well and
trauma is autopoetic right the more
traumatized i am the more likely i am to
behave in ways that will perpetuate
trauma to myself and others
so trauma healing and actually
dealing with the underlying bases of
rivalrous conditioning in ourselves
and learning how to have more authentic
and effective relationships and
communication with other people this is
all super important
the place where so that's all stuff i'm
inspired by i'll tell you
the place where i'm concerned about it
is where
where people actually get overwhelmed by
the problems of the world they seem too
big so they say well i'm just going to
focus on my own healing and the world
will
magically shift through the
morphogenetic field change as our
consciousness elevates
or the right solutions will kind of
magically emerge
out of this and it's actually
a way of disconnecting
from what they care about in the world
and yet
feeling some sense of um soothing or
or agency and so
you know one thing i would say is any
psychology
that is helping people actually be more
okay with the things they shouldn't be
okay with
is not good
so helping people just be at peace with
institutionalized violence
and um you know broken systems
like i i am very glad that someone
didn't
talk gandhi in the early days
into just understanding that personal
development and working on ourselves and
becoming the change in our own self was
the only thing to do and to not
have like to not focus on the british
empire because
that was just an expression of his own
upset and unhealed traumas
um you'll notice that
you know whether it's jesus with the
romans and the jews or
martin luther king with the current
state of affairs regarding black people
or gandhi with regard to the british
empire like they weren't
they weren't actually trying to just be
peaceful with what is
they actually cared about then reality
enough
that there were things where they're
like this actually needs to change
and i'm interested in the kind of psycho
spiritual development that empowers me
to change it not the kind that is kind
of like spiritual
opiates yeah i've listened to
all of your podcasts all the appearances
you've made i think i've read everything
on civilization emerging
i think there are a lot of people like
at least in my weird corner
of the internet and the sign of
subcultures that i participate in who
are kind of like
looking to you for answers solutions and
the way forward and i i guess i'm like
curious about
you personally like how are you relating
uh are you like aware that there's that
kind of expectation
or that that's put on you or that people
look to you that way and like what's it
like
to be that person around such like
deeply critical
topics well i feel like
you know i've i've had the fortune to
spend a lot of time with people that
have helped me make sense of the world a
lot
and a lot of them people who don't speak
publicly because they're
oriented to be making sense of the world
rather than other things
and then you know been able to
bring a number of frameworks together
that
seem like they are
adding useful clarity to the ability to
make sense of the world and
um you know what i'm
i'm focused on how do we actually design
solutions to these problems but i'm also
focused on
just you know in the last couple years
starting to share some of these
frameworks in a way that can hopefully
support
as you're mentioning an up leveling of
the collective
consciousness intelligence consideration
around these things so that
you know not just those of us who are
working together but in a decentralized
way
more people are informed
by the things that i have found useful
uh
and so insofar as some of those things
that resonate with me are resonating
with other people i feel
happy about that and
you know it's interesting there's
something that i think about like when
you're asking though what do we do
if we think about the psychology of
people who have done
fundamental pioneering and fundamental
invention and discovery they don't ever
get to ask anyone else how to do what
they're doing
right like that's intrinsic to the
nature of figuring out new stuff
is that you can't ask anyone else how to
do it now that doesn't mean that you
don't learn from
a tremendous amount of stuff and stand
on the shoulders of giants but then if
you're newton you're standing on the
shoulders of giants you're making sure
you've learned those things
but you're also then advancing the edge
and there's
there's a kind of
there's a kind of psychology that is
necessary
to be willing to work at something that
nobody can tell you how to do
and that there's no precedent in a
history of smart people at figuring out
and it's not hubris it's just a depth of
care that
can't turn away
and there's like the i can't not focus
on this
so even though i have no idea if i'll
succeed i still have to be working on it
and you know i think that
growing up as kids most of us got most
of our praise
from doing things that the authorities
wanted us to do
and that had already been figured out so
we got the right answer to
to answers in sunday school that the
teachers had already
predetermined what the right answer was
or in actual school where we figured out
how to spell our math or whatever
or winning a game where the rules of the
game were set or doing the chores where
we didn't really have a say in the
nature of how the house was designed or
and so we get all this praise for doing
things that are already figured out
that someone else tells us to do
and almost all the times we got punished
were for doing something that we wanted
to do
and so there's a very deep psychological
program
that is running that has to be unwound
because that psychology is itself one of
the generator functions of the problem
it keeps
people perpetuating the existing systems
and so
you know if someone asks me well what
should i do
i'm more interested in the meta question
of like
how do you i can share some things with
you and a number of people can share
some things with you
but how do you navigate
sovereignty in a way that says when i
come to the edge of things that
aren't known how do i figure out what to
do how do i discover
stuff as opposed to do stuff that
somebody else told me is the thing to do
like that there's a there's a
psychological shift there that is really
critical so that's one thing
and coming together with other people
that are also really
earnestly endeavoring to figure out how
to do things that they care about that
aren't currently known and figuring out
how to actually
collaborate in that together so how to
be in it ourself and how to collaborate
with others in it
and this requires it this actually
requires a mature relationship
with certainty and uncertainty where i
can sit in
uncertainty about something that's
really consequential i don't know how to
solve the problems of the world yes it
really matters i don't know how to solve
even this particular problem yes it
matters
but i can sit in the uncertainty which
also means the uncomfort of it
so that i don't just have to distract
myself with something else
or default to a quick answer that's the
wrong answer because i need some
certainty
so there's a psychologic willingness to
sit in the discomfort of that
uncertainty
but there's also a psychological
willingness to go through the epistemic
process
to bring about enough certainty to act
so it's easy for us to be very
uncomfortable with uncertainty and want
certainty fundamentalism
of all kinds does that but it's also
very easy for us to
to kind of do the post-modern move and
be uncomfortable with any certainties
and be sure that all certainty is
imperialism
and only need to rest in uncertainty
which means we never have an epistemic
basis for good choice
and so a mature relationship to reality
knows that there is knowable and
unknowable stuff
and within the knowable there's mostly
unknown
and some known and that even the known
my epistemic confidence margin is not a
hundred percent
and yet there are better confidence
margins than others as a basis for
action
and a mature relationship to all that
says that i can sit with uncertainty
and i can sit with certainty both
comfortably
emotionally so that i'm not being
emotionally biased one way or the other
and i can explore what is the right
process
to bring about a particular confidence
margin for the certainty to act
i think that people who haven't received
a lot of
attention often
misassess how uncomfortable it is
um and miss assess that it'll actually
be fun
yeah um
you know i i had whatever wounded
childhood dynamics that
created insecurity that sought external
approval
like everybody does and figured out my
what i can be good at to get approval
strategies and i remember the first
times that i
was like speaking somewhere
that had respectable
people respecting me and should have
been some kind of
success in that way and i remember
feeling
really terrible as the people were
focusing on being stoked on me
because they weren't focusing on
actually caring about the issues and
what they could do about it they were
focusing on me
and that was like actually doesn't do
for me
and i'm like no no don't do that
i'm talking about these issues because i
care about them hoping to connect to
where you care about them and i'm i have
any insights because i have to because i
care about them enough i keep working on
it and i want to know
how we can kind of collaborate together
but focusing on
me in a way where you get to say like oh
i'm glad he's working on that like
that's actually dreadful
um so
uh yeah you know i i think that's kind
of interesting
getting to be part of conversations
with people who are really earnestly
working on stuff is obviously meaningful
and also getting to be in conversations
that increase my sense making about the
world is meaningful
and i will say that well you know mostly
i talk about ideas
that i'm hoping give people frames to
make sense of the world that empower
whatever they're doing if we never talk
or interact
you know if they're if there are people
who are very called to
how do we make new systems and who
have um developed some capacities in
some of these areas
there are things that we're researching
that could use
support and research and so if if there
are people who would like to
explore the possibility of um
engaging and supporting some
sense-making uh
send me a message well thank you so much
daniel for for taking the time to to
speak about all this and um as we kind
of head towards the closing of the
conversation i'm curious like
is there anything uh at this point
that's on your heart or mind that you
feel like would be uh would be
good to presence before we close this
conversation up
i really like what you're doing with
this podcast
and um you know the
the fact that you listened to all of the
things and read all the things you did
and
you have really worked to make sense and
then want to
help advance the conversation and are
connected to the
you know it seems like you have a
community of people
that are all kind of at the
front of a bell curve of really trying
to make sense of certain things in the
world
and working you know you're working to
empower them to do a better job with
that
and you know when you ask where are
there things that are emerging that i
feel good about this would be an example
[Music]
oh
so
[Music]
china
uh
[Music]
huh
you